<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wordplay | rspeer]]></title>
  <link href="http://rspeer.github.io/blog/categories/wordplay/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rspeer.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-30T19:46:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rspeer.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Speer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Speln Ncorrector]]></title>
    <link href="http://rspeer.github.io/blog/2011/03/01/speln-ncorrector/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-01T18:18:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rspeer.github.io/blog/2011/03/01/speln-ncorrector</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I was experimenting with using a machine translation toolkit on problems
besides translation. My first experiment was to try to make a system that would
take in a word it hasn&rsquo;t seen before and guess how it was pronounced.</p>

<p>I think I accidentally ran something backwards, because what I got was a system
that takes in the legitimate pronunciation of a word, and usually outputs a
creative new spelling that it hasn&rsquo;t seen before.</p>

<p><em>I have created a spelling incorrector.</em></p>

<p>Or, as it would say when I put the CMUDICT pronunciations of these words in:</p>

<blockquote><p>Tude I wuz expermentn wth usin a mhin translaun tulkt on problems besids
translaun.  M furst experment wuz 2 tri 2 mak a sstm thet wood tak in a
word t haznt syn byfor and gs hu t wuz pranonst.</p>

<p>I think I axedently ran sumthn bakwards, bkuz wut I gt wuz a sstm thet takz
in the logitamt prenanseaun v a word, and ugly otputs a creatv nu speln
thet t haznt syn byfor.</p>

<p>I hav creatd a speln ncerector.</p></blockquote>

<p>I am not kidding. Those are the actual spellings my backwards-wired system
gives for dictionary pronunciations of those words, including spelling
&ldquo;usually&rdquo; as &ldquo;ugly&rdquo;, &ldquo;accidentally&rdquo; as &ldquo;axedently&rdquo;, and &ldquo;to&rdquo; as &ldquo;2&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The CONFUZZLE wordlist]]></title>
    <link href="http://rspeer.github.io/blog/2011/02/21/confuzzle/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-21T23:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rspeer.github.io/blog/2011/02/21/confuzzle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://rspeer.github.io/images/confuzzle-sample.png" /></p>

<p>There are lots of text files that list the words you can use in word games like
Scrabble. (Some of them are more accurate than others.) But as far as I know,
this is the only one that you can print on 17 double-sided sheets of
letter-size paper.</p>

<p>The words in the list come from the excellent, public-domain ENABLE2K word
list, compiled by Mendel Cooper. His website is sadly defunct, but the wordlist
has become a standard for word games and puzzles.</p>

<ul>
<li>The file: <a href="/downloads/confuzzle.pdf">confuzzle.pdf</a></li>
<li>LaTeX source: <a href="/downloads/confuzzle.tex">confuzzle.tex</a></li>
<li>The source wordlist: <a href="/downloads/enable.txt">enable.txt</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Why would you want a wordlist on paper instead of a computer file? The same
reason you&rsquo;d want to play word games on a board instead of on a computer.
Sometimes, you&rsquo;d rather face the person you&rsquo;re playing against than have your
face in a laptop.</p>

<h2>How the list works</h2>

<p>The list only contains words, not their definitions. Still, given that there
are over 170,000 words in the list, it takes some effort &mdash; beyond just using a
6-point font &mdash; to fit them on 34 pages.</p>

<p>This economy of printed space is accomplished through a form of human-readable
compression. When many consecutive words in alphabetical order start with the
same letters, as they tend to do, they are grouped together like this:</p>

<pre><code>ALLOTYP- e es ic ically ies y
</code></pre>

<p>The grouping was chosen by an algorithm, not by a lexicographer, so sometimes
words are grouped in odd ways:</p>

<pre><code>NONSOL- ar id ids ution utions
</code></pre>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also marked the differences between ENABLE and the more well-known
standard, the Official Tournament and Club Word List 2 (OWL2). These markings
are not authoritative, because I don&rsquo;t have an electronic file of OWL2. I
compiled the differences mainly from <a href="http://www.scrabbleassociation.com/boards/dictionary/octwl2.html">this National Scrabble Association
page</a>.</p>

<p>Locating the code that chose the groupings will, unfortunately, take a bit of
hard-drive archaeology. I made the list in 2003, updated it for OWL2 in 2006,
and updated it manually in 2011 to incorporate the National Scrabble
Association&rsquo;s errata to OWL2.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
